"Update on Erythritol Sweetener Safety:
Are There Side Effects?"
It’s funny, when you search
for information
about the low-calorie
sweetener erythritol
in the scientific literature,
you stumble across papers like this,
describing a use for erythritol
that I had not imagined.
But you think that’s explosive?
What about headlines like these?
Erythritol associated with increased
body fat in young adults,
metabolic dysfunction,
coronary heart disease,
heart failure, pre-diabetes,
full-blown diabetes,
and diabetic complications
like kidney damage and blindness.
But wait,
I thought erythritol
has been reported
to be a totally safe
and even have
anti-oxidant properties.
Let’s take a closer look
at these studies.
Upon entering college,
many young adults
experience weight gain—
the dreaded “freshman 15”—
which can start them off
on the wrong course in life
in terms of developing
chronic illness.
But not all freshmen do;
so, researchers wanted to try
to tease out why some
gained weight
and others didn’t.
So, on one of their
first days at school
a bunch of students
got their blood drawn,
and then nine months later
were reweighed
and got more blood taken.
About a quarter of the students
maintained a stable weight,
but the other three quarters gained
an average of about nine pounds.
Then, they did something
interesting.
They pooled the blood of all
those who remained stable
and compared that
to the collection
of blood from all
the gainers
to see if they could
pick out any differences.
And the ones who gained weight
had significantly higher levels
of erythritol in their blood,
and not just by a little—
15 times higher levels.
Those found to have poor
blood sugar control
had 21 times higher
blood erythritol levels.
And the same thing
with heart disease.
What did people
who developed heart disease
have more in their blood
than those that didn’t?
Erythritol.
The same thing with diabetes
and diabetes complications.
Okay, so what’s going on?
Is erythritol contributing to obesity,
and heart disease, and diabetes,
or is it just
an innocent bystander?
Maybe it’s reverse causation,
meaning instead of erythritol
leading to more weight gain,
maybe weight gain
led to more erythritol.
After all, who tends to go
for the low-calorie sweeteners?
But wait a second.
In this study, for example,
they took blood before
and after a period of over 20 years.
Was erythritol
even around back then?
The first blood draws
were in the 80s,
and erythritol wasn’t
approved until 2001.
Same thing with
the heart disease study.
The blood samples
were taken in the late 80s;
so, the presence of erythritol
in their blood cannot be explained
by consumption of erythritol
as a sugar replacement.
So, wait.
How did they end up
with so much erythritol
in their system?
Their own body made it.
We know that your body
can take excess blood sugar
and convert it into erythritol.
If you give people
radioactively labeled sugar,
within two hours
radioactively labeled erythritol
shows up in your blood.
It turns out erythritol
is a pentose-phosphate
pathway metabolite,
meaning that’s the pathway
by which blood sugar
is converted into erythritol.
And the pentose-phosphate pathway
is a protective pathway.
It's a way your body disposes
of excess blood sugar
by trying to convert
the sugar to other things
to bring down blood sugar levels.
So, having erythritol
in your system
seems to be a consequence
of too high sugars, not the cause.
So, no wonder erythritol
is associated with diabetes.
That may be just like saying
high blood sugar levels
are associated with
high blood sugar levels.
And high blood sugars
are also associated
with obesity and heart disease.
In fact, erythritol synthesis
could be an adaptive mechanism
to counter the oxidative stress
induced by obesity
and high blood glucose.
In other words, not just
a way to reduce blood sugar,
but since erythritol
can act as an antioxidant,
maybe your body
is making it
specifically to help
sop up the mess.
The bottom line is that
there are no studies
linking the consumption
of erythritol
to any disease outcomes.
But the flip side
of that is yeah,
the studies that have been
done on erythritol do show
it to be relatively innocuous
and possibly beneficial,
but the effects of chronic
erythritol consumption
have not been evaluated
either way.
That’s where the science was,
until 2023, when a prestigious lab
out of Cleveland Clinic
found increased clotting
susceptibility in human blood
in a test tube and mouse
blood in a mouse artery.
That was at blood concentrations
like 45 micromoles, or even 290.
But have people chug two
tablespoons of the stuff
and erythritol blood levels
jump up into the thousands
within a matter of minutes.
And so, until we have clinical
studies exonerating the stuff,
I would recommend people to
stay away from erythritol.